Guide to the William Dunlap Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
William Dunlap collection
1786-1835
YCAL MSS 498
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.63
(2 boxes)
The collection consists chiefly of bound manuscript diaries and corresponding typescript transcriptions. Also included in the collection is a bound manuscript recipe book, two letters, and a theater script translated into English from French by Dunlap entitled Thirty Years or The Life of a Gamester or The Gambler's Fate.
Dunlap, William, 1766-1839
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired from various sources. Provenance is listed at folder level when known.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Existence and Location of Copies
Microfilm service copies are available for: Manuscript bound diary, 1820 August 9-1822 April 21 (film number 755).
Associated Materials
Miniatures owned by Yale University Art Gallery. Some diaries are owned by the New York Historical Society.
William Dunlap, 1766-1839
William Dunlap, American producer, playwright, actor, and historian.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists chiefly of bound manuscript diaries and corresponding typescript transcriptions. Also included in the collection is a bound manuscript recipe book, two letters, and a theater script translated into English from French by Dunlap entitled "Thirty Years or The Life of a Gamester or The Gambler's Fate."
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Diaries, 1786-1833. II. Other Papers, 1813-1835.
Dramatists, American; Diaries -- United States -- 18th century; Diaries -- United States -- 19th century; Theater scripts; Dramatists; Dunlap, William, 1766-1839
- Diaries, 1786-1833, undated; Series I; 0.42; (1 box)
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Gift of Theodore Salisbury Woolsey, December 1922.
  - Bound manuscript diaries
    - "Walking trip from London to Oxford", 1786 (Box 1)
    - 1798 June 1-1798 December 15 (Box 1)
    - 1806 January 1-1808 September 21, 1806-1808 (Box 1)
    - 1811 March 17-1813 May 7, 1811-1813 (Box 1)
    - 1820 August 9-1822 April 21, 1820-1822 (Box 1)
    - 1832 March 16-1833 June 25, 1832-1833 (Box 1)
  - Typescript transcriptions of diaries, undated; 6 (Box 1)
- Other Papers, 1813-1835, undated; Series II; 0.21; (1 box)
  Scope and Contents
  Removed from printed material cataloged separately. Further information on provenance is in each folder.
  - Bound manuscript recipe book, undated (Box 2)
  - Letters to Matthew Cary and unidentified "Gentlemen...", 1813 June 1, 1832 (Box 2)
    Removed from books in the library of Owen Aldis.
  - 'The American Vasari," autograph manuscript of paper on Dunlap, miscellaneous notes on the same; a receipt, signed " William Dunlap, 1835 January 9;" and typed letter signed to Woolsey from E.W.H. Newport, no year January 25; two engraved cards, 1835, undated (Box 2)
    Gift of Heathcote Woolsey, May 1957.
  - "Thirty Years or The Life of a Gamester or The Gambler's Fate," theater script, handwritten bound. Translated from the French by Dunlap., undated (Box 2)
    Gift of Owen Aldis, 1911.